<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="atom.xsl"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://noorg.dev/blog</id>
    <title>Noorg Blog</title>
    <updated>2024-12-20T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://noorg.dev/blog"/>
    <subtitle>Noorg Blog</subtitle>
    <icon>https://noorg.dev/img/noorg_logo.png</icon>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Embrace Plain Text and LSP The Future of Noorg]]></title>
        <id>https://noorg.dev/blog/noorgs-future-and-plaintext</id>
        <link href="https://noorg.dev/blog/noorgs-future-and-plaintext"/>
        <updated>2024-12-20T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[banner]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="banner" src="https://noorg.dev/assets/images/banner-acd6a13721d595172de9501e7deb7452.png" width="800" height="200" class="img_ev3q">
<strong>Why Plain Text Matters: A Deep Dive into Endless Possibilities</strong>p</p>
<p>Explore <a href="https://noorg.dev/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Noorg</a>. The following is a deep dive into the endless possibilities of plain text and how it forms the foundation of tools like Noorg.</p>
<p>In the digital age, where note-taking tools are abundant and varied, plain text remains a cornerstone of simplicity, adaptability, and freedom. Why does plain text still matter, and how does it empower us to think beyond traditional paradigms? Let’s explore the endless possibilities of plain text and how it forms the foundation of innovative tools like Noorg.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>Plain Text: Simplicity Meets Power</strong></p>
<p>Plain text is not just a format—it’s a philosophy. It’s about embracing the fundamental nature of data as readable, writable, and universally accessible.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Universality:</strong> Plain text can be opened, read, and edited by any text editor on any operating system. From <code>notepad.exe</code> to Vim, from Visual Studio Code to nano, the options are endless.</li>
<li><strong>Longevity:</strong> Proprietary formats may come and go, but plain text endures. A <code>.txt</code> file from the 1980s is still as accessible today as it was back then.</li>
<li><strong>Portability:</strong> Plain text doesn’t lock you into a specific tool or ecosystem. Your data remains yours.</li>
<li><strong>Processability:</strong> Plain text can be manipulated in infinite ways. Whether through scripts, command-line utilities, or full-fledged applications, plain text’s flexibility is unmatched.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p><strong>Plain Text: Beyond Display</strong></p>
<p>The beauty of plain text lies in its raw nature. It’s only text, but its simplicity opens doors to infinite interpretations and transformations:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Dynamic Processing:</strong> Metadata, tags, and structure can be added with simple conventions, like Markdown or frontmatter. Tools then transform these annotations into actionable insights.</li>
<li><strong>Programmable Interactions:</strong> You can parse, analyze, and process plain text with any programming language. Imagine a plain text note becoming a task list, a calendar entry, or a project tracker—all through automation.</li>
<li><strong>Unlimited Potential:</strong> The constraints of plain text are only defined by how it’s displayed. Text can be visualized as tables, diagrams, timelines, or any other form that suits your needs.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p><strong>The Noorg Approach: Watchers Today, LSP Tomorrow</strong></p>
<p><a href="https://noorg.dev/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Noorg</a> currently uses a background application and watcher pattern to process notes dynamically. While this approach is functional, it’s not the final form. Let’s break down why:</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="watchers-the-current-state">Watchers: The Current State<a href="https://noorg.dev/blog/noorgs-future-and-plaintext#watchers-the-current-state" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Watchers: The Current State" title="Direct link to Watchers: The Current State">​</a></h3>
<p>Noorg’s watcher monitors changes in your notes directory. When a file is saved, observers written in Rust, Python, or Lua react to those changes. This pattern provides real-time processing and flexibility but comes with challenges:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Redundancy:</strong> File watchers reimplement functionality already covered by other systems, like file system events or editor-specific plugins.</li>
<li><strong>Integration Complexity:</strong> Although Noorgs is cross editort, the setup process can be cumbersome, requiring manual configuration and installation.</li>
<li><strong>Cross-Platform Challenges:</strong> File watchers behave differently across operating systems, complicating implementation.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-future-a-language-server-protocol-lsp-implementation">The Future: A Language Server Protocol (LSP) Implementation<a href="https://noorg.dev/blog/noorgs-future-and-plaintext#the-future-a-language-server-protocol-lsp-implementation" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to The Future: A Language Server Protocol (LSP) Implementation" title="Direct link to The Future: A Language Server Protocol (LSP) Implementation">​</a></h3>
<p>The Language Server Protocol (LSP) offers a standardized way to communicate between editors and background processes. By transitioning to an LSP-based architecture, Noorg can achieve:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Editor-Agnostic Integration:</strong> Nearly every modern editor supports LSP. This means Noorg would work seamlessly with VSCode, Neovim, Emacs, Sublime Text, and more without separate plugins.</li>
<li><strong>Centralized Functionality:</strong> Observers and metadata processing can be handled by the LSP server, reducing redundancy and simplifying updates.</li>
<li><strong>Rich Features:</strong> With LSP’s capabilities, Noorg could provide contextual suggestions, dynamic views, and inline annotations directly within the editor.</li>
<li><strong>Ease of Shipping:</strong> Building and shipping for all editors becomes as simple as distributing the LSP server. Editors handle the integration, reducing Noorg’s maintenance burden.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="maintaining-observer-power">Maintaining Observer Power<a href="https://noorg.dev/blog/noorgs-future-and-plaintext#maintaining-observer-power" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Maintaining Observer Power" title="Direct link to Maintaining Observer Power">​</a></h3>
<p>An LSP-based Noorg would retain the full power of current observers. Scripts written in Rust, Python, or Lua could still process notes dynamically. The difference? Observers would hook into a unified, editor-friendly framework. For example:</p>
<ul>
<li>Observers could add metadata in real-time as you type.</li>
<li>Dynamic views, like Kanban boards or tag-based summaries, could be rendered directly in the editor.</li>
<li>Advanced features, like inline content restructuring or API integrations, would become simpler to implement.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p><strong>Plain Text + LSP: The Ultimate Combination</strong></p>
<p>By embracing the simplicity of plain text and the power of LSP, Noorg can evolve into a truly universal tool. Here’s what this combination unlocks:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Offline First, Forever:</strong> Plain text ensures your data remains accessible, while LSP ensures rich functionality without cloud dependencies.</li>
<li><strong>Infinite Extensibility:</strong> Use any programming language to build integrations, observers, and automations.</li>
<li><strong>Universal Editor Support:</strong> Write in any editor, from Vim to VSCode, and let Noorg handle the heavy lifting.</li>
<li><strong>Future-Proof:</strong> Standardized protocols and open formats ensure longevity and compatibility.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="embrace-the-plain-text-revolution">Embrace the Plain Text Revolution<a href="https://noorg.dev/blog/noorgs-future-and-plaintext#embrace-the-plain-text-revolution" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Embrace the Plain Text Revolution" title="Direct link to Embrace the Plain Text Revolution">​</a></h2>
<p>Plain text is more than a format—it’s a gateway to creativity and control. With tools like Noorg, the potential of plain text is unlocked, empowering you to focus on what matters: your ideas.</p>
<p>As Noorg transitions to an LSP-based architecture, its flexibility and power will only grow, making it an indispensable tool for anyone who values simplicity, adaptability, and innovation. Join us in embracing plain text and building a future where note-taking is as limitless as your imagination.</p>
<hr>
<p><em>Explore Noorg on <a href="https://github.com/realjockel/noorg" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">GitHub</a> and become part of the plain text revolution. Let’s redefine what note-taking can be.</em></p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>realjockel</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/realjockel</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="announcement" term="announcement"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Noorg is born 🎉]]></title>
        <id>https://noorg.dev/blog/noorg-is-born</id>
        <link href="https://noorg.dev/blog/noorg-is-born"/>
        <updated>2024-12-04T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[banner]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="banner" src="https://noorg.dev/assets/images/banner-acd6a13721d595172de9501e7deb7452.png" width="800" height="200" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="capture-everything-organize-nothing-"><strong>Capture Everything, Organize Nothing</strong> 📝<a href="https://noorg.dev/blog/noorg-is-born#capture-everything-organize-nothing-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to capture-everything-organize-nothing-" title="Direct link to capture-everything-organize-nothing-">​</a></h2>
<p>In a world with an abundance of note-taking tools, <strong>Noorg</strong> offers a different approach to managing your thoughts, ideas, and knowledge. Whether you're a developer, a creative, or simply someone who loves to take notes, Noorg was designed with one core principle: <strong>focus on capturing ideas, not organizing them</strong>.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="why-noorg-"><strong>Why Noorg?</strong> 🤔<a href="https://noorg.dev/blog/noorg-is-born#why-noorg-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to why-noorg-" title="Direct link to why-noorg-">​</a></h2>
<p>Traditional note-taking systems often demand meticulous organization, rigid hierarchies, and time-consuming curation. Noorg is here to liberate you from these constraints. Inspired by the philosophy of <strong>"just write it down"</strong>, Noorg shifts the focus from organization to effortless <strong>capture</strong> and <strong>processing</strong>.</p>
<p>Imagine being able to:</p>
<ul>
<li>Write freely in any editor of your choice (Vim, Emacs, VSCode, Obsidian—you name it).</li>
<li>Automatically annotate and process notes using <strong>dynamic metadata</strong>.</li>
<li>Extend functionality with powerful integrations written in <strong>Python, Lua, and Rust</strong>.</li>
<li>Focus on what matters most: your ideas.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="who-is-noorg-for-"><strong>Who Is Noorg For?</strong> 🌟<a href="https://noorg.dev/blog/noorg-is-born#who-is-noorg-for-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to who-is-noorg-for-" title="Direct link to who-is-noorg-for-">​</a></h2>
<p>Noorg is for everyone who wants a tool that adapts to their workflows rather than the other way around. It’s ideal for:</p>
<ul>
<li>Developers who prefer working in their favorite editors.</li>
<li>Writers who need a system that doesn’t get in the way of creativity.</li>
<li>Knowledge workers tired of rigid folder structures and endless tagging.</li>
<li>Hobbyists who want to experiment with automation and integrations.</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="warning-note-noorg-is-currently-in-pre-alpha-so-expect-bugs-and-instability-your-feedback-is-crucial-to-shaping-its-future-also-it-is-only-available-for-macos-currently">⚠️<!-- --> <strong>Note</strong>: Noorg is currently in <strong>pre-alpha</strong>, so expect bugs and instability. Your feedback is crucial to shaping its future. Also it is only available for MacOS currently.<a href="https://noorg.dev/blog/noorg-is-born#warning-note-noorg-is-currently-in-pre-alpha-so-expect-bugs-and-instability-your-feedback-is-crucial-to-shaping-its-future-also-it-is-only-available-for-macos-currently" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to warning-note-noorg-is-currently-in-pre-alpha-so-expect-bugs-and-instability-your-feedback-is-crucial-to-shaping-its-future-also-it-is-only-available-for-macos-currently" title="Direct link to warning-note-noorg-is-currently-in-pre-alpha-so-expect-bugs-and-instability-your-feedback-is-crucial-to-shaping-its-future-also-it-is-only-available-for-macos-currently">​</a></h2>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-makes-noorg-special-"><strong>What Makes Noorg Special?</strong> ✨<a href="https://noorg.dev/blog/noorg-is-born#what-makes-noorg-special-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to what-makes-noorg-special-" title="Direct link to what-makes-noorg-special-">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="editor-agnostic-and-seamless-integration-"><strong>Editor-Agnostic and Seamless Integration</strong> 🔗<a href="https://noorg.dev/blog/noorg-is-born#editor-agnostic-and-seamless-integration-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to editor-agnostic-and-seamless-integration-" title="Direct link to editor-agnostic-and-seamless-integration-">​</a></h3>
<p>Noorg is not tied to any specific editor, meaning you can use it with your favorite tools. Write in Markdown, enrich your notes with frontmatter metadata, and let Noorg handle the rest.</p>
<hr>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="dynamic-observers-"><strong>Dynamic Observers</strong> 👀<a href="https://noorg.dev/blog/noorg-is-born#dynamic-observers-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to dynamic-observers-" title="Direct link to dynamic-observers-">​</a></h3>
<p>Leveraging the <strong>observer pattern</strong>, Noorg provides real-time note processing without breaking your flow. For instance:</p>
<ul>
<li>A <strong>time tracker</strong> monitors how much time you spend on topics.</li>
<li><strong>Inline tags</strong> dynamically create a tagging system.</li>
<li>Observers can even generate a daily journal or tag notes based on content.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="extensible-runtime-"><strong>Extensible Runtime</strong> 🔧<a href="https://noorg.dev/blog/noorg-is-born#extensible-runtime-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to extensible-runtime-" title="Direct link to extensible-runtime-">​</a></h3>
<p>At its heart, Noorg is a highly extensible runtime. Want to customize it? Use <strong>Python</strong>, <strong>Lua</strong>, or <strong>Rust</strong> to build your own note-processing workflows, from automatic tagging to complex data integrations. The possibilities are endless:</p>
<ul>
<li>Create <strong>Kanban boards</strong> for project tracking.</li>
<li>Automate <strong>time tracking</strong> and <strong>task prioritization</strong>.</li>
<li>Develop custom <strong>dynamic views</strong> with SQL-like queries.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="offline-first-and-free-"><strong>Offline-First and Free</strong> 🌐<a href="https://noorg.dev/blog/noorg-is-born#offline-first-and-free-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to offline-first-and-free-" title="Direct link to offline-first-and-free-">​</a></h3>
<p>Noorg respects your privacy and autonomy. It’s fully offline, with no cloud dependencies, free, and open source. Your notes stay with you, and the community drives its growth.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="use-cases-what-can-you-do-with-noorg-"><strong>Use Cases: What Can You Do with Noorg?</strong> 💡<a href="https://noorg.dev/blog/noorg-is-born#use-cases-what-can-you-do-with-noorg-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to use-cases-what-can-you-do-with-noorg-" title="Direct link to use-cases-what-can-you-do-with-noorg-">​</a></h2>
<ol>
<li><strong>Dynamic Journaling</strong>: Automatically compile a daily journal from your notes.</li>
<li><strong>Kanban Boards</strong>: Organize tasks visually.</li>
<li><strong>Tagging Systems</strong>: Use inline tags to categorize and create dynamic note views.</li>
<li><strong>Time Tracking</strong>: Monitor your focus and productivity.</li>
<li><strong>Custom Automation</strong>: Build workflows with Python, Lua, or Rust, such as integrating APIs or generating reports.</li>
</ol>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="why-noorg-was-created-️"><strong>Why Noorg Was Created</strong> 🛠️<a href="https://noorg.dev/blog/noorg-is-born#why-noorg-was-created-%EF%B8%8F" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to why-noorg-was-created-️" title="Direct link to why-noorg-was-created-️">​</a></h2>
<p>Noorg was born out of frustration with overly complex note-taking systems. It’s for the thinkers who just want to capture their thoughts without the cognitive overhead of organizing them. It's for those who value simplicity, adaptability, and innovation in their tools.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="caution-pre-alpha-stage-️"><strong>Caution: Pre-Alpha Stage</strong> ⚠️<a href="https://noorg.dev/blog/noorg-is-born#caution-pre-alpha-stage-%EF%B8%8F" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to caution-pre-alpha-stage-️" title="Direct link to caution-pre-alpha-stage-️">​</a></h2>
<p><strong>Caution</strong>: Noorg is currently in a pre-alpha stage. While it offers powerful features, it is still under active development and may not be stable. We strongly advise starting slowly and backing up your note directory regularly. Experiment with Noorg in a safe environment to discover its potential without risking your important data.</p>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="join-the-noorg-community-"><strong>Join the Noorg Community</strong> 🤝<a href="https://noorg.dev/blog/noorg-is-born#join-the-noorg-community-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to join-the-noorg-community-" title="Direct link to join-the-noorg-community-">​</a></h2>
<p>Noorg is <strong>free</strong>, <strong>open source</strong>, and <strong>community-driven</strong>. We believe in building tools together that empower people to think freely and creatively. Join us on this journey to redefine note-taking.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/realjockel/noorg" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">GitHub Repository</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/realjockel/noorg#readme" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Documentation</a></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="get-started-today-"><strong>Get Started Today</strong> 🚀<a href="https://noorg.dev/blog/noorg-is-born#get-started-today-" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to get-started-today-" title="Direct link to get-started-today-">​</a></h2>
<p>Install Noorg and experience a new way of managing your thoughts:</p>
<p>Start here:</p>
<p><a href="https://noorg.dev/docs/intro">Get Started</a></p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>realjockel</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/realjockel</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="announcement" term="announcement"/>
    </entry>
</feed>